<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<wrstart>
    <topic subject="campaign_travel">
        <date>November 21, 1963</date>
        <locations>
            <location>Texas</location>
            <description>President Kennedy and First Lady Jacqueline Kennedy travel to Texas for a two-day, five-city tour</description>
        </locations>
        <purpose>
            <description>Political campaigning for the 1964 presidential election, with a focus on winning key states, including Texas and Florida</description>
        </purpose>
        <events>
            <event>
                <date>November 21, 1963</date>
                <location>San Antonio, Houston, Fort Worth</location>
                <description>Campaign stops for military preparedness and economic growth, with a breakfast at the Fort Worth Chamber of Commerce</description>
            </event>
        </events>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="morning_in_fort_worth">
        <date>November 22, 1963</date>
        <location>Texas Hotel, Fort Worth</location>
        <weather>Light rain</weather>
        <event>
            <description>President Kennedy addresses a crowd of thousands in the parking lot outside the hotel, emphasizing national defense and leadership.</description>
        </event>
        <breakfast>
            <description>President speaks to the Fort Worth Chamber of Commerce about military preparedness</description>
        </breakfast>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="on_to_dallas">
        <date>November 22, 1963</date>
        <location>Dallas, Texas</location>
        <event>
            <description>President and Mrs. Kennedy board a motorcade from Love Field Airport to the Trade Mart in downtown Dallas, waving to the crowd along the way</description>
        </event>
        <details>
            <description>The motorcade is in an open convertible, with the plastic top removed due to the clear weather.</description>
        </details>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="assassination">
        <date>November 22, 1963</date>
        <time>12:30 p.m.</time>
        <location>Dealey Plaza, Dallas, Texas</location>
        <incident>
            <description>Gunshots are fired at President Kennedy as the motorcade turns off Main Street. Kennedy is struck in the neck and head.</description>
            <consequence>President Kennedy slumps over toward Mrs. Kennedy; Governor Connally is also wounded.</consequence>
            <hospital>
                <location>Parkland Memorial Hospital</location>
                <result>President Kennedy is pronounced dead at 1:00 p.m. A priest administers the last rites.</result>
            </hospital>
        </incident>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="transition_of_power">
        <date>November 22, 1963</date>
        <time>2:38 p.m.</time>
        <location>Love Field, Dallas</location>
        <event>
            <description>Vice President Lyndon B. Johnson is sworn in as President aboard Air Force One</description>
            <officiator>US District Court Judge Sarah Hughes</officiator>
        </event>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="lee_harvey_oswald">
        <date>November 22, 1963</date>
        <location>Dallas, Texas</location>
        <incident>
            <description>Lee Harvey Oswald is arrested for the assassination of President Kennedy and the murder of Patrolman J.D. Tippit.</description>
        </incident>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="jack_ruby">
        <date>November 24, 1963</date>
        <event>
            <description>Jack Ruby, a nightclub owner, shoots and kills Lee Harvey Oswald while he is being transferred to the county jail.</description>
            <consequence>Oswald dies two hours later at Parkland Hospital.</consequence>
        </event>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="president_kennedy_funeral">
        <date>November 25, 1963</date>
        <location>Arlington National Cemetery</location>
        <event>
            <description>President Kennedy's funeral is held with heads of state from around the world in attendance. His flag-draped casket is transported on a caisson, accompanied by a riderless black horse.</description>
        </event>
        <final_grave_site>
            <description>President Kennedy is buried at Arlington National Cemetery, with an eternal flame lit by his widow Jacqueline Kennedy and his brothers Robert and Edward.</description>
        </final_grave_site>
    </topic>
    <topic subject="warren_commission">
        <date>November 29, 1963</date>
        <event>
            <description>President Lyndon B. Johnson appoints the Warren Commission to investigate the assassination of President Kennedy.</description>
            <commission_chairman>Chief Justice Earl Warren</commission_chairman>
        </event>
        <findings>
            <summary>The Warren Commission concludes that Lee Harvey Oswald acted alone in the assassination.</summary>
        </findings>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="house_select_committee_on_assassinations">
        <date>1976</date>
        <event>
            <description>The US House of Representatives establishes the House Select Committee on Assassinations to re-investigate the Kennedy assassination.</description>
        </event>
        <findings>
            <summary>The Committee finds a "high probability" of two gunmen firing at President Kennedy, though this conclusion is later challenged.</summary>
        </findings>
    </topic>
    
    <topic subject="assassination_records_collection">
        <date>1992</date>
        <legislation>
            <description>The President John F. Kennedy Assassination Records Collection Act mandates the declassification and release of assassination-related documents.</description>
            <location>National Archives and Records Administration</location>
        </legislation>
    </topic>
</wrstart>
