<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--To be merged with LHOBioPt.1-->
<!--I would of liked to have refined this further, but it will suit the projects needs ~Daniel-->
<?xml-model href="WRProjectSchemaBasic.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<wrstart>
 <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> took his wife and children to Love Field, the Dallas
 airport, to meet <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> and Marina and their baby, <person
  perid="June-Lee-Oswald">"June Lee</person>. He testified that the most noticeable change in his
 brother&apos;s appearance was that he had become rather bald; he seemed also to be somewhat thinner
 than he had been in 1959. <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> thought that his brother
 had picked up <quote speaker="Robert-Oswald">something of an accent</quote> but, except for these
 changes was <quote speaker="Robert-Oswald">the same boy</quote> whom he had known before. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> commented on the absence of newspaper reporters and seemed
 to <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> to be disappointed that none had appeared. Later
 on, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> was anxious to avoid publicity. <person
  perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> drove <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person> to his home at <place plaid="1501-West-Seventh-Street">7313 Davenport
  Street</place>. For a few days, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> seemed tense, but
 the brothers got along well, and to <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> it was <quote
  speaker="Robert-Oswald">more or less ... [as if <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person>]
  had not been to Russia</quote>; they were <quote speaker="Robert">just together again.</quote>
 They did not discuss politics, according to <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> because
 of a <quote speaker="Robert-Oswald">tacit agreement</quote> between them. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> indicated to his brother that he hoped to have his
 undesirable discharge from the Marines corrected. <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> and
 his wife <quote speaker="Robert">took to Marina and <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald"
  >June</person>,</quote> and enjoyed showing Marina <quote speaker="Robert">things that she had
  never seen before.</quote> Marina rested and took care of her baby, and when she could, helped in
 the household. She testified that, apart from a trip to the library, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> spent about a week <quote speaker="Marina">"merely
  talking.</quote> On <date daid="June-18">June 18</date>, 4 days after he arrived in Fort Worth,
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> went to the office of Mrs. Pauline Virginia
 Bates, a public stenographer whose name he had found in the telephone directory, and asked her to
 type a manuscript from the <quote speaker="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">scraps of paper,</quote> on which he
 had recorded his impressions of the Soviet Union. Intrigued by his tale that he had just returned
 from the Soviet Union and had smuggled his notes out of that country, she agreed to type the notes
 for $1 per page or $2 an hour, 50 cents less than her usual hourly rate. On that day and the
 succeeding 2 days, Mrs. Bates spent 8 hours typing for <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> while he remained in her office helping her with the notes and translating
 portions of them which were in Russian. At the end of each session he collected his notes and as
 much of the manuscript as she had done and took them away with him. On <date daid="June-20">June
  20</date>, he gave Mrs. Bates $10 for the 10 completed pages; he told her that he had no more
 money and refused to accept her offer to postpone pay-merit or continue the work for nothing.
 Oswald told Mrs. Bates that there was an engineer in Fort Worth who wanted to help him publish his
 notes. On <date daid="June-19">June 19</date>, he had called Peter Gregory, a petroleum engineer
 who was born in Siberia and taught Russian at the Fort Worth Public Library as a <quote
  speaker="unspecified">civic enterprise</quote>. He asked if Gregory could give him a letter
 testifying to his ability to read and speak Russian, so that he could obtain work as an interpreter
 or translator. Gregory suggested that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> come to his
 office, where Gregory opened a Russian book at random and asked <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> to read from it. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> read well, and
 Gregory gave him the letter he wanted. Gregory and <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> had lunch together and discussed <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person>&apos;s life in the Soviet Union, but, according to Gregory&apos;s testimony,
 nothing was said about publishing <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s
 manuscript. About a week later, Gregory and his son Paul, a college student, visited <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> at <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert
  Oswald</person>&apos;s home and arranged for Marina to give Paul lessons in Russian during the
 summer. On <date daid="June-26">June 26</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 was interviewed by FBI agents in Fort Worth. One of the agents who interviewed him described him as
 tense and <quote speaker="unspecified">drawn up</quote>; he said that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 <quote speaker="unspecified">exhibited an arrogant attitude ... and [was] inclined to be just a
  little insolent.</quote>
 <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> declined to say why he had gone to Russia, saying
 that he refused to <quote speaker="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">relive the past.</quote> He said that he had
 not attempted to obtain Soviet citizenship, had not been approached by Soviet officials for
 information about his experiences in the Marines, and had not offered them such information.
 Marina&apos;s Soviet passport required her to notify the Soviet Embassy in Washington of her
 address in this country, and <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told the agents that
 he planned to contact the Embassy for this purpose within a few days. He promised to notify the FBI
 if he were contacted by Soviet agents <quote speaker="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">under suspicious
  circumstances or otherwise.</quote>
 <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told his brother about the interview, saying that
 it had been <quote speaker="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">just fine.</quote> Oswald and his family remained
 with <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> for about a month. While they were there his
 mother moved to Fort Worth from Crowell, Tex., and sometime in July they moved into her apartment
 at <place plaid="1501-West-Seventh-Street">1501 West Seventh Street</place>. <person
  perid="Marguerite-Oswald">Mrs. Oswald</person> testified that she had visited them at <person
  perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person>&apos;s house in June and moved to Fort Worth because she
 thought that the house was too crowded and wanted to help them. <person perid="Marguerite-Oswald"
  >Mrs. Oswald</person> described the period when her son and his family lived with her as <quote
  speaker="">a very happy month</quote>; according to her testimony, she and her son and
 daughter-in-law got along well. She mentioned that she not only helped Marina keep house and care
 for the baby but also aided her son in his efforts to find employment. Marina testified, however,
 that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> did not get along well with his mother and that
 he decided after several weeks that they should move to their own apartment. He did not file a
 change-of-address card at the post office when the family moved to West Seventh Street, as he did
 when they made their next move, so he may have contemplated from the beginning that they would stay
 with his mother for only a short while. Around the middle of August, <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> moved to a one-bedroom furnished
 apartment at<place plaid="2703-Mercedes-Street">2703 Mercedes Street</place>, for which they paid
 $59.50 in advance for 1 month&apos;s rent. In the third week in July, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had obtained a job as a sheet metal worker with the
 Louv-R-Pak Division of the Leslie Welding Co., a manufacturer of louvers and ventilators, to which
 he had been referred by the Texas Employment Commission. On his application for employment, filled
 out several days before, he wrote falsely that he had experience as a sheet metal worker and
 machinist in the Marines and had been honorably discharged. He usually worked 8 or 9 hours a day,
 for which he was paid $1.25 an hour. Marina testified that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> did not like his work, but he was regarded as a good employee and remained with
 the company until October, when he quit. On the job, he kept to himself and was considered
 uncommunicative. <person perid="Marguerite-Oswald">Mrs. Oswald</person> visited her son and his
 family at their apartment and tried to help them get settled; she testified that she bought some
 clothes for Marina and a highchair for the baby but that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> told her that he did not want her to buy <quote speaker="">things for his wife
  that he himself could not buy.</quote> Finally, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 apparently decided that he did not want his mother to visit the apartment anymore and he became
 incensed when his wife permitted her to visit despite his instructions. After he moved to Dallas in
 October, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not see his mother or communicate
 with her in any way until she came to see him after the assassination. Witnesses have described the
 Mercedes Street apartment as <quote speaker="">decrepit</quote> and very poorly furnished; there
 was no telephone service. Acquaintances observed that Marina and the baby were poorly clothed, that
  <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> had little food, and that at
 first there was not a bed for the baby. On <date daid="August-16">August 16</date>, the FBI again
 interviewed <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>. This interview took place in the
 back seat of a car in front of his home and covered substantially the same material as the previous
 interview. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> again denied having made any deal with
 representatives of the Soviet Union. He protested his undesirable discharge from the Marines, and
 stated that his wife was registered at the Soviet Embassy. He still refused to discuss why he had
 gone to the Soviet Union, but he was less hostile than he had been during the previous interview.
 According to his wife, however, he was very upset by the interest the FBI showed in him. <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">The Oswalds</person> became acquainted with a growing number
 of people of the Russian-speaking community in the Dallas-Fort Worth area, who were tied together
 socially by a common origin, language, and religion. The group was not restricted to people from
 Russia but was composed primarily of people from Eastern European countries. <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">The Oswalds</person>&apos; initial contact with this group
 was through Peter Gregory. Marina gave conversational Russian lessons to Paul Gregory 2 days a week
 during August and early September, for which she was paid $35. Most of the lessons took place at
 the Mercedes Street apartment and <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was generally
 present. In addition, Paul Gregory occasionally took <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >the Oswalds</person> shopping; after they became friendly, he had a number of discussions with
 Oswald, some of them politically oriented. Sometime around <date daid="August-25">August 25</date>,
 Peter Gregory invited <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> and several
 members of the Russian community to his house for dinner. One of the guests was George Bouhe, a
 Dallas accountant and a leader of the Russian community. He was very interested in meeting and
 conversing with Marina, because she had spent much of her life in Leningrad, which was his
 birthplace. Also present was Mrs. Anna Meller, the Russian- born wife of a Dallas department store
 employee. Near the end of August, <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>
 met Declan Ford, a consulting geologist in the Dallas area, and his Russian-born wife at Mrs.
 Meller&apos;s home. <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">The Oswalds</person> were also
 introduced to Mrs. Elena Hall, who was born in Tehran, Iran, of Russian parentage. She worked in a
 dental laboratory and at this time was divorced from her former husband John Hall, whom she
 subsequently remarried. In order to obtain dental aid for Marina, George Bouhe had brought her to
 Mrs. Hall&apos;s house. In early September, <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person> met Alexander Kleinlerer, another member of the Russian group, who was then
 courting Mrs. Hall. Mrs. Max Clark was introduced to Marina during this period by George Bouhe and
 Anna Meller. Max Clark met <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> at a
 later time. At about the same time, they were visited by George De Mohrenschildt, a petroleum
 engineer born in Russia. who had heard of them from one of the Russian-speaking group. Later on,
  <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> met his wife, Jeanne, and his
 daughter and son-in-law, Gary and Alexandra Taylor. Most of the members of the Russian community
 were interested in <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> not only
 because they needed help, but also because they could provide the latest information about what was
 happening in Russia. Some members of the group were at first apprehensive about them because the
 apparent ease with which they had left Russia seemed suspicious. Nevertheless, many of the group
 provided small amounts of money, groceries, clothing, and furniture for <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>; George Bouhe, Anna Meller, and Elena
 Hall were the primary contributors, although others provided help in the form of transportation and
 groceries. These acquaintances occasionally visited <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >the Oswalds</person>, and <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> in
 turn visited some of them in Dallas. It was evident that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> did not appreciate the help of the Russian community. At least once he flew into
 a rage and shouted that he did not need any of the things that people were giving to him. Some felt
 that he resented the gifts because he could not give his wife what the others were providing;903 he
 apparently was critical of them also because he felt that they were overly concerned with improving
 themselves economically. Oswald became increasingly unpopular with his Russian-speaking
 acquaintances, partly because of his resentment of their assistance. Alexander Kleinlerer stated
 that none of them cared for <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 <quote speaker="">because of his political philosophy, his criticism of the United States, his
  apparent lack of interest in anyone but himself and because of his treatment of Marina.</quote>
 Some of them believed that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was mentally
 disturbed. However, they felt sorry for Marina and the child and continued to help. On a weekend
 afternoon early in October, <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> were
 visited by his mother and a number of people from the Russian community, including George Bouhe,
 Anna Meller, the Halls, the De Mohrenschildts, and the Taylors. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> had apparently decided to look for a new job, and discussed his lack of job
 prospects and the fact that his rent was overdue. He was advised to seek employment in the Dallas
 area. Elena Hall invited Marina to move into her house in Fort Worth until <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> found a job in Dallas. She accepted the proposal, and
 Mrs. Hall moved Marina. her daughter <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>, and the
 Oswalds&apos; few household goods in a pickup truck belonging to the dental laboratory where she
 was employed. Oswald worked at the Leslie Welding Co. on Monday, <date daid="October-8">October
  8</date>, but failed to appear on the following day. He was already in Dallas. He falsely told his
 wife that he had been discharged, and told George Bouhe that the job had been a temporary one.
 Sometime later, the company received an undated letter from him stating that he had <quote
  speaker="">moved permanently to Dallas,</quote> and asking that the wages due him be forwarded to
 him at box <place plaid="box-2915-in-Dallas">2915 in Dallas</place>. He did not tell his mother
 that he was leaving Fort Worth. While they were in Fort Worth, <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> were having marital problems. Several
 people noted that Marina had a blackened eye when they visited her at the Mercedes Street
 apartment. She told her mother-in-law and George Bouhe that her husband had struck her, but said to
 Anna Meller that she had walked into a door. It seems clear that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> had in fact hit her. People observed friction between <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> on various occasions, although their
 disputes became more apparent later. Marina has written that this was a difficult period for them
 and that her husband was <quote speaker="">very irritable</quote> and sometimes some completely
 trivial thing would <quote speaker="">drive him into a rage.</quote> She testified that: ...
 immediately after coming to the United States <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person>
 changed. I did not know him as such a man in Russia. ... He helped me as before, but he became a
 little more of a recluse ... He was very irritable, sometimes for a trifle ... She has denied,
 however, that their separation was the result of quarrels between them. Marina spent the first few
 weeks after <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s departure at Elena Hall&apos;s
 house in Fort Worth, except for a brief stay at Gary Taylor&apos;s house in Dallas after one of her
 appointments at the Baylor Dental Clinic. While she was in Dallas, Mrs. De Mohrenschildt brought
 her to the clinic on <date daid="October-8">October 8</date>, <date daid="October-10">October
  10</date>, and <date daid="October-15">October 15</date>; George Bouhe had given Mrs. De
 Mohrenschildt the money to cover the expense of Marina&apos;s dental care. Even before <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> went to Dallas, some of his acquaintances were helping
 him in his effort to find a job there. George De Mohrenschildt directed him to Samuel B. Ballen, a
 Dallas financial consultant, but no employment resulted. George Bouhe recommended that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> go to the Texas Employment Commission in Dallas; and
 Anna Meller had her husband ask Mrs. Helen Cunningham, a counselor in the clerical and sales
 division of the Dallas office of the employment commission, to help <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> find a job. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> first came into the office of the employment commission on <date daid="October-9"
  >October 9</date>. He was reluctant to accept industrial employment, and was placed in the
 clerical category and turned over to Mrs. Cunningham for counseling. He indicated that he had an
 interest in writing. The results of general aptitude tests which he had taken at the Fort Worth
 employment office had been transmitted to the Dallas office, and indicated that he had some
 aptitude in this direction and for clerical work. It was noted on his application form that he had
  <quote speaker="">outstanding verbal-clerical potential.</quote> He demonstrated ability to
 perform many skilled and semi-skilled jobs, and there was some indication that he could do college
 work. Mrs. Cunningham gave him three special tests: for general clerical work, work as an insurance
 claims examiner, and drafting work. He scored high on all three. His application form indicated
 that he did not have a driver&apos;s license, and noted: <quote speaker="">well-groomed and spoken,
  business suit, alert replies--expresses self extremely well.</quote> He told Mrs. Cunningham that
 he hoped to develop qualifications for responsible junior executive employment by a work-study
 program at a local college but that this must be delayed because of his immediate financial needs
 and responsibilities. Mrs. Cunningham concluded that although <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> would be classified for clerical work, she should try to get him any available
 job, since he badly needed money. He was referred to an architect for an opening as a messenger but
 was not hired. On <date daid="October-11">October 11</date>, he was referred to
 Jaggars-Chiles-Stovall Co., a graphic arts company, in response to a call from John Graef, head of
 the photographic department of the company, who had told the employment commission that he needed a
 photoprint trainee. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was enthusiastic about his
 prospects and apparently made a good impression; Graef picked him over several other applicants. On
 the following day he began working in his new position as a trainee making prints of advertising
 material. He worked a 40-hour week at approximately $1.35 per hour; his take-home pay varied from
 $49 to $74 a week. According to his wife, <quote speaker="">he liked his work very much.</quote>
 Oswald moved into the YMCA on <date daid="October-15">October 15</date>, and stayed there until
  <date daid="October-19">October 19</date>, paying $2.25 a night. He had used the Taylors&apos;
 address and telephone number as a place where he could be reached, but on <date daid="October-9"
  >October 9</date> had also rented post office box <place plaid="box-2915">2915</place> under his
 own name at the main post office on Ervay Street. On <date daid="October-10">October 10</date>, he
 filed a change-of-address form indicating that mail for <place plaid="2703-Mercedes-Street">2703
  Mercedes Street</place> should be forwarded to the box. Marina has written that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> wrote her letters and telephoned her during the
 separation. On <date daid="October-16">October 16</date>, Mrs Hall brought Marina and <person
  perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person> to Dallas to have <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald"
  >June</person> baptized. Marina apparently did this surreptitiously, because her husband opposed
 baptism; they did not contact him in Dallas, but left birthday gifts for him at the Taylors.
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not appear very disturbed when he found out
 about the baptism. Two days later, Mrs. Hall had an automobile accident and went to the hospital,
 where she remained until <date daid="October-26">October 26</date>; Marina remained in the Hall
 house. Mrs. Max Clark and Alexander Kleinlerer, a friend of Mrs. Hall, checked up to make sure that
 she was getting along without too much trouble. After <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> left the YMCA on <date daid="October-19">October 19</date>, he moved to a room or
 apartment somewhere in Dallas, which has not been located. It seems likely, however, that during
 that time he spent several weekends with Marina at the Hall house. Four days after Mrs. Hall
 returned from the hospital, she left for New York to visit friends. By the time she returned,
 Marina had moved to a three-room apartment at <place plaid="604-Elsbeth-Street-in-Dallas">604
  Elsbeth Street in Dallas</place>, which <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had
 rented on Saturday, <date daid="November-3">November 3</date>; the landlady stated that he had
 looked at the apartment about a week before. The monthly rent was $68, in addition to which he had
 to pay several dollars a month for utilities. He paid the rent plus a $5 deposit on <date
  daid="November-3">November 3</date>, but probably spent that night with Marina at the Hall house.
 On Sunday the Taylors helped <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> move
 their belongings to the Elsbeth Street apartment with a rented trailer. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had asked Kleinlerer to help them move, and Kleinlerer
 also was present when they departed. Soon after <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person> were reunited, their marital difficulties started again. While they were moving
 to Elsbeth Street, Kleinlerer noticed that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 slapped his wife for not having the zipper on her dress completely closed. They argued over his
 refusal to allow her to smoke. There was a quarrel also when he told the landlady that Marina was
 from Czechoslovakia; he was angered when Marina, who disapproved of this deception, told the
 landlady the truth. Although several people tried to help Marina improve her scanty knowledge of
 English, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> discouraged this, perhaps because he
 wanted to keep up his Russian. Some witnesses testified that she commented about his sexual
 abilities. He apparently continued to beat her, and once she suggested to George De Mohrenschildt
 that she should <quote speaker="">get away</quote> from <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person>. When De Mohrenschildt criticized <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person>&apos;s conduct, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> replied, <quote
  speaker="">It is my business.</quote> Marina testified that when they moved into the Elsbeth
 Street apartment, her husband became <quote speaker="">nervous and irritable</quote> and was very
 angry over <quote speaker="">trifles.</quote> She said that it was sometimes her fault that he beat
 her, for example when she wrote to an old boyfriend in Russia that she wished she had married him;
 the letter was returned for postage due, and <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> read
 it. Because of this quarreling, a few of their acquaintances felt that Marina would be better off
 alone. George Bouhe offered to help her if she promised to leave <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> permanently. Finally, in early November, Marina, helped by the De Mohrenschildts,
 moved into Anna Meller&apos;s house with the intention not to return to <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>. He was apparently quite upset and did not want Marina
 to leave him. Oswald did not visit his wife at Anna Meller&apos;s house, and for a short time did
 not even know where she was. According to Marina, he called her after she moved and they met at De
 Mohrenschildt&apos;s house. He asked her to return home. She insisted that he stop quarreling and
 that he change his ways. He said that he could not change. Marina would not agree to return home
 with him and he left. Marina was uncomfortable at the Meller house, where there was very little
 room. She moved to Katherine Ford&apos;s house where she apparently stayed from <date
  daid="November-11to17">November 11 to 17</date>. She indicated that she had decided never to
 return to her husband; it was Mrs. Ford&apos;s impression that Marina was going to stay at other
 people&apos;s houses until a permanent place could be found for her. When Mr. Ford returned from a
 business trip on <date daid="November-17">November 17</date>, Marina and <person
  perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person> moved to the home of Mrs. Frank Ray, where they spent the
 day. Mrs. Ray, the wife of a Dallas advertising man, was also of Russian origin. Since Mrs. Ray had
 no baby bed, Marina returned to the Fords that evening. On the next day, however, Marina moved her
 belongings to the Rays&apos; house. That same day, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> called and asked to visit his wife, whom he had called and written. Mr. Ray
 picked him up and took him to Marina. Marina testified that at this meeting <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> professed his love for her. She stated: <quote
  speaker="">I saw him cry ... [he] begged me to come back, asked my forgiveness, and promised that
  he would try to improve, if only I would come back.</quote> On another occasion she said: <quote
  speaker="">... he cried and you know a woman&apos;s heart--I went back to him. He said he
  didn&apos;t care to live if I did not return?</quote> That same day she decided to return to him.
 Mr. Ray packed her belongings and took her back to the Elsbeth Street apartment. Members of the
 Russian community who had taken care of Marina so that she would not have to live with <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> felt that their efforts had been in vain. George Bouhe
 was so irritated that he never again tried to help either of <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>. Contacts between them and members of
 the Russian community diminished markedly. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did
 not care for most of these people and made his feelings apparent. Even the De Mohrenschildts, whom
 he liked most, saw much less of them. Lydia Dymitruk, another Russian born woman in the Dallas-Fort
 Worth area, testified that she saw <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person> on only one occasion, and did not care to see them again. She drove Marina and
  <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>, who had a high fever, to the hospital; <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told the hospital that he was unemployed in order to
 avoid paying for <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>&apos;s treatment and later left Mrs.
 Dymitruk without thanking her. Mrs. Ford testified that Marina had told her that she contemplated
 suicide during this period because <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was treating
 her badly and she had no friends; she felt that she had <quote speaker="">no way out.</quote>
 Marina acknowledged to the Commission that she had such thoughts. In an effort to renew family
 ties, <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert Oswald</person> wrote to <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> and John Pic on <date daid="November-17">November
 17</date>, inviting them and their families to Thanksgiving dinner. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> accepted the invitation. He and Marina traveled to Fort
 Worth by bus on Thanksgiving Day, and John Pic and <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person>
 met them at the station. Pic had not seen his half-brother for 10 years. He observed, as many
 others have also attested, that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> seemed to be a good
 father and to take an active interest in <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>. After
 dinner, Marina phoned Paul Gregory, who later drove <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >the Oswalds</person> to his house for sandwiches and then took them to the bus station for the
 return trip to Dallas. Thereafter, <person perid="Robert-Oswald">Robert</person> spoke to his
 brother once by telephone and received a post card and a letter from him, but he eventually lost
 contact with <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> and did not see him again until after
 the assassination. Despite his disillusionment with Soviet life, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> kept up his interest in Russia. He wrote to the Soviet Embassy in Washington for
 information on how to subscribe to Russian periodicals and for <quote speaker="">any periodicals or
  bulletins which you may put out for the benefit of your citizens living, for a time, in the
  U.S.A.</quote> He subsequently subscribed to several Russian journals. In <date
  daid="December-1962">December 1962</date>, the Soviet Embassy received a card in Russian, signed
  <quote speaker="">Marina and <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee Oswald</person>,</quote> which
 conveyed New Year&apos;s greetings and wishes for <quote speaker="">health, success and all of the
  best</quote> to the employees at the Embassy. <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">The
  Oswalds</person> continued to correspond with acquaintances in Russia. Soon after his return to
 this country, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had started to correspond with the
  <person perid="Communist-Party-U.S.A.">Communist Party, U.S.A.</person>, and the Socialist Workers
 Party. He subscribed to the Worker in <date daid="August-1962">August 1962</date>. He wrote for
 additional literature from these organizations, and attempted to join the Socialist Workers Party,
 which, however, had no branch in Texas. He sent samples of his photographic work to the Socialist
 Workers Party, the Worker, and the Hall-Davis Defense Committee, and offered to aid them in
 printing and photographic work in connection with posters; these offers were not accepted. He
 continued to read a great deal on a variety of subjects. George Bouhe testified that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s fare consisted of books by Marx, Lenin, <quote
  speaker="">and similar things.</quote> Marina said that he read books of a historical nature,
 including H. G. Wells&apos; two volume <quote speaker="">Outline of History,</quote> and
 biographies of Hitler, Kennedy, and Khrushchev. Despite <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>&apos; break with the Russian community,
 De Mohrenschildt, knowing that they would be alone during the Christmas season, asked the Fords
 whether he could bring <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> to a party
 celebrating the Russian Christmas at the Fords&apos; home; the Fords assented. The party was
 attended by many members of the Russian community. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> spoke at length with Yaeko Okui, a Japanese woman who had been brought to the
 party by Lev Aronson, first cellist of the Dallas Symphony Orchestra; she told Federal
 investigators that she never saw <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> again. <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">The Oswalds</person> were not invited to three other Russian
 Christmas season gatherings which occurred during the next few days. Marina visited the De
 Mohrenschildts several times after Christmas. They invited both <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Lee</person> and Marina to a small dinner party in February 1963; also present were Everett
 Glover, a chemist employed in Dallas, and his roommate Volkmar Schmidt. On February 22, Glover had
 a gathering at his house, one of the purposes of which was to permit his friends, many of whom were
 studying Russian, to meet <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>. They
 were the objects of much attention. Marina conversed at length with another guest named Ruth Paine,
 who had recently separated from her husband, Michael Paine, a research engineer at the Bell
 Helicopter plant in Fort Worth. Mrs. Paine, who was studying Russian, obtained Marina&apos;s
 address and shortly thereafter wrote Marina asking to see her. Marina responded by inviting Mrs.
 Paine to visit her. <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">The Oswalds</person> moved out of
 their Elsbeth Street apartment on <date daid="March-3">March 3</date>, 1963, to an upstairs
 apartment several blocks away at <place plaid="214-West-Neely-Street">214 West Neely
 Street</place>. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> inquired about the apartment in
 response to a <quote speaker="">For Rent</quote> sign; the rent was $60 per month, not including
 utilities. They moved without assistance, carrying their belongings in their hands and in a baby
 stroller. Marina preferred the Neely Street apartment because it had a porch and was, she felt,
 more suitable for <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>. Aware of <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s difficulties in obtaining employment, George
 Bouhe had advised him as early as <date daid="10/1962">October/1962</date> to attend a night school
 in Dallas. On <date daid="January-14">January 14</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> enrolled in a typing course in the night school of Crozier Technical High School,
 and started attending on <date daid="January-28">January 28</date>. The class ran from 6:15 to 7:15
 p.m. on Mondays, Tuesday, and Thursdays. Although <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 reviewed a typing textbook at home, he attended the course irregularly and stopped going altogether
 on about <date daid="March-28">March 28</date>. Ruth Paine and Marina started to exchange visits in
 March. Mrs. Paine invited <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> for
 dinner, and on <date daid="April-20">April 20</date> she took them on a picnic. When <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was not present, the two women frequently discussed
 their respective marital problems, and Marina disclosed to Mrs. Paine that she was pregnant. Marina
 wrote of these meetings: One day we were invited to a friend&apos;s house, where I met Ruth Paine,
 who was studying Russian here in America and wanted to improve her conversational knowledge. We
 began to see each other. Ruth would come to see me with her children. This was very good for both
 me and for <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>. She was growing up alone and becoming
 terribly wild, so the company of other children was good for her. Sometimes we went out on picnics
 at a nearby lake. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> loved to fish, and we would look
 and rejoice if he caught a little fish. Several times we went to visit Ruth who lived in Irving.
 Using the name of <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald-Alias">A. J. Hidell, Oswald</person> had ordered
 a Smith &amp; Wesson .38 revolver from Los Angeles on a form which he dated <date daid="January-27"
  >January 27</date>. On <date daid="March-12">March 12</date>, he ordered a rifle from Klein&apos;s
 Sporting Goods in Chicago under the name of <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald-Alias">A. Hidell.
  Oswald</person> used the name <quote speaker="">Alek James Hidell</quote> on identification cards
 which he probably produced at Jaggars-Chiles-Stovall. One of his fellow employees taught him
 various photographic techniques, which he could have used to prepare not only these cards, but also
 the samples of his work which he sent to various organizations. Both weapons were shipped on <date
  daid="March-20">March 20</date>. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> kept the rifle
 in a small storeroom at the Neely Street apartment. He spent long periods of time in the storeroom,
 which he told Marina she was not to enter. He told her that he intended to use the rifle for hunt-
 ing and that he practiced with it. She saw him leave with it once, and clean it several times. He
 also posed for two pictures, taken by Marina in the backyard of the Neely apartment, in which he
 held his rifle and copies of the Worker and the Militant and the revolver was strapped to his belt.
 He gave one of the pictures to his wife and asked her to keep it for <person
  perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>. Over the weekend of <date daid="March-9-10">March
  9-10</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> photographed the alley which runs
 behind the home of Gen. Edwin Walker, and probably at about the same time he photographed the rear
 of Walker&apos;s home and a nearby railroad track and right-of-way. He prepared and studied a
 notebook in which he outlined a plan to shoot General Walker, and he looked at bus schedules. He
 went to the Walker residence on the evening of <date daid="April-6">April 6</date> or 7, planning
 to make his attack. However, he changed his plans, hid his rifle nearby, and determined to act on
 the following Wednesday, <date daid="April-10">April 10</date>, when a nearby church was planning a
 meeting which, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> reasoned, would create a diversion
 that would help him escape. On Wednesday, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> left a
 note for Marina telling her what to do if he were apprehended. He retrieved his rifle and fired at
 Walker, but the bullet narrowly missed Walker&apos;s head. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> secreted his rifle again and took the bus home. When <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told Marina what he had done, she became angry and made
 him promise never to repeat such an act. She testified that she kept his letter, intending to give
 it to the authorities if he repeated his attempt. He told Marina that he was sorry he had missed
 Walker and said that the shooting of Walker would have been analogous to an assassination of
 Hitler. Several days later, the De Mohrenschildts visited <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>, bringing an Easter present for <person
  perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>. During the visit, Jeanne De Mohrenschildt saw the rifle and
 told her husband about it. Without any knowledge of the truth, De Mohrenschildt jokingly intimated
 that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was the one who had shot at Walker. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> apparently concluded that Marina had told De
 Mohrenschildt of his role in the attempt and was visibly shaken. On <date daid="April-6">April
  6</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was dropped by Jaggars-Chiles-Stovall
 because, in his supervisor&apos;s opinion, he could not do the work, although he was trying; in
 addition, he did not get along with his fellow employees. The fact that he brought a Russian
 newspaper to work may also have been of some significance. Marina testified that her husband, who
 had always worried about his job security at Jaggars-Chiles-Stovall, was quite upset by the loss of
 his job since he had liked the work. Oswald again resorted to the Texas Employment Commission. On
  <date daid="April-8">April 8</date>, he informed the Commission that he was seeking employment but
 was referred to no employers. He stated that he had been laid off at Jaggars-Chiles-Stovall due to
 lack of work." On <date daid="April-12">April 12</date>, he made a claim for unemployment benefits;
 4 days later the commission mailed him a determination disapproving his claim because of
 insufficient wage credits. For a while after <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person> moved into the Neely Street apartment they got along well, but they soon began to
 quarrel. Oswald was apparently still preventing Marina from learning English, and there is some
 indication that he continued to beat her. Since February, he had been urging her to return to
 Russia. Marina wrote several letters to the Russian Embassy requesting a visa to return to Russia.;
 she testified, however, that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> forced her to write
 them, and that she never wanted to return to Russia. When Ruth Paine visited <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> at their apartment on <date
  daid="April-24">April 24</date>, she was surprised to learn that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> was packed and ready to leave for New Orleans by bus. He explained that he had
 been unable to find employment in or around Dallas, and that Marina had suggested that he go to New
 Orleans since he had been born there. Marina has testified that the real reason behind her
 suggestion was that she wanted to get him out of town because of the Walker incident. Mrs. Paine
 offered to drive Marina to New Orleans at a later date, and also to have Marina and <person
  perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person> stay with her rather than at the apartment in the meantime.
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> helped the women pack Mrs. Paine&apos;s car, and
 the two women moved everything from the Neely Street apartment to the Paine house in Irving. When
 he arrived at the bus station in New Orleans, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 telephoned his aunt, Lillian Murret, to ask if he could stay at her home at <place
  plaid="757-French-Street">757 French Street</place> while he looked for employment. She had been
 unaware that he had returned from Russia or that he was married and had a child and was surprised
 to hear from him. She said that she did not have room to accommodate three guests, but that since
 he was alone he was welcome. Oswald had been born in New Orleans, and on his return showed great
 interest in finding out what had happened to the other members of his father&apos;s family. He
 visited the cemetery where his father was buried and called all <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> in the telephone book. By this method he
 located one relative, <person perid="Hazel-Oswald">Mrs. Hazel Oswald</person> of Metairie, La., the
 widow of <person perid="William Stout Oswald">William Stout Oswald</person>, his father&apos;s
 brother. He visited her at her home; she gave him a picture of his father and told him that as far
 as she knew the rest of the family was dead. On <date daid="April-26">April 26</date>, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> began his search for employment. He went to the
 employment office of the Louisiana Department of Labor and stated that he was qualified as a
 commercial photographer, shipping clerk, or <quote speaker="">darkroom man.</quote> The interviewer
 noted on <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s application card: <quote
  speaker="">Will travel on limited basis. Will relocate. Min. $1.25 hr. Neat. Suit. Tie.
  Polite.</quote> Although the employment commission made a few referrals, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> relied primarily upon newspaper advertisements, and
 applied for a number of positions. Mrs. Murret testified that he would spend the day job hunting,
 return to her home for supper, watch television, and go to bed. On <date daid="April-29">April
  29</date>, he filed a request for reconsideration of the employment commission&apos;s disapproval
 of his unemployment compensation claim. His complaint that he had not been credited for his
 employment at Jaggars-Chiles-Stovall was ruled valid on <date daid="May-8">May 8</date>, and he was
 granted maximum benefits of $369, payable at the rate of $33 per week. He filed interstate claims
 on <date daid="May-7">May 7</date> and 15, and received $33 in response to the latter; the former
 claim was filed before the expiration of the prescribed wailing period. Not only had <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> in fact been working since <date daid="May-10">May
  10</date>, but he included on his claim sheet, as concerns with which he had sought work,
 fictitious employers and employers whom he apparently had not contacted. Oswald wrote to Marina:
  <quote speaker="">All is well. I am living with Aunt Lillian. She has very kindly taken us in. I
  am now looking for work. When I find it I will write you.</quote> And on <date daid="May-3">May
  3</date>, he wrote to Marina and Ruth Paine: <quote speaker="">Girls, I still have not found work,
  but I receive money from the unemployment office in the amount 15 to 20 dollars. They were
  mistaken in the Dallas office when they refused, but I straightened everything out. Uncle
  &apos;Dyuz&apos; offered me a loan of $200.00 if needed. Great, eh?!</quote> On <date daid="May-9"
  >May 9</date>, responding to a newspaper advertisement, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> completed an application for employment with William B. Reily Co., Inc., at
  <place plaid="640-Magazine-Street">640 Magazine Street</place>, an enterprise engaged in the
 roasting, grinding, canning, bagging, and sale of coffee. On his application form, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> listed as references in addition to John Murret, <quote
  speaker=""><person perid="Sgt.-Robert-Hidell">Sgt. Robert Hidell</person></quote> and <quote
  speaker=""><person perid="Lieut. J. Evans">Lieut. J. Evans</person>,</quote> both apparently
 fictitious names. His application was approved and he began work on <date daid="May-10">May
  10</date>, at the rate of $1.50 per hour. His task was the lubrication of the company&apos;s
 machinery. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not enjoy this work, and told his
 wife and Mrs. Paine that he was working in commercial photography. Also on <date daid="May-9">May
  9</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> obtained an apartment at <place
  plaid="4905-Magazine-Street">4905 Magazine Street</place> with the help of Myrtle Evans, who had
 known him when he was a child. The rent was $65 a month. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> moved in on <date daid="May-10">May 10</date>, after telephoning Marina on the
 ninth and asking her to come to New Orleans. Ruth Paine testified that the invitation elated
 Marina: <quote speaker="">Papa nas lubet</quote>--"Daddy loves us," she repeated again and again.
 Mrs. Paine drove Marina and <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person> to New Orleans; they left
 Dallas on <date daid="May-10">May 10</date>, spent the night in Shreveport, and arrived on the
 11th. Mrs. Paine stayed with <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> for
 8 days; the three of them, with <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person> and Mrs. Paine&apos;s
 children, toured the French Quarter. On <date daid="May-14">May 14</date>, Mrs. Paine left New
 Orleans to return to her home. The Murrets and <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person> exchanged visits from time to time; Marina testified that the Murrets were very
 good to them. Mrs. Murret&apos;s daughter, Marilyn, took <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> on an outing. But, according to
 Marina&apos;s testimony, aside from Ruth Paine and Ruth Kloepfer and her daughters, the Murrets
 were the only social visitors <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>
 had. Ruth Kloepfer was a clerk of the Quaker Meeting in New Orleans whom Ruth Paine had written in
 the hope that she might know some Russian-speaking people who could visit Marina. Mrs. Kloepfer
 herself visited <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person> but made no
 attempt to direct any Russian-speaking people to them. On <date daid="July-19">July 19</date>,
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was dismissed by Reily because of inefficiency
 and inattention to his work. He had spent many of his working hours next door at the Crescent City
 Garage, where he read gun magazines and discussed guns with one of the owners, Adrian Alba. On the
 following Monday, <date daid="July-22">July 22</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> again visited the Louisiana employment office to seek new employment and file a
 claim for unemployment compensation. Thereafter, he collected unemployment compensation weekly and,
 although apparently making some effort to obtain another job, again listed a number of fictitious
 job applications on his unemployment compensation claim forms. He soon gave up his search for
 employment, and began to spend his days at home reading. He received another setback on <date
  daid="July-25">July 25</date>, when he was notified that in response to the request for review
 which he had made in 1962, his undesirable discharge from the Marine Corps had been affirmed.
 During this period, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> began to evidence thoughts of
 returning to the Soviet Union or going to Cuba. On <date daid="June-24">June 24</date> he applied
 for a new passport, which he received on the following day. Apparently at <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s request, Marina wrote to the Russian Embassy,
 expressing a desire to return to Russia and indicating that she would be accompanied by her
 husband. She explained that she wanted to return because of family problems, including the
 impending birth of her second child. Accompanying her letter was a letter written by <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> dated <date daid="July-1">July 1</date>, in which he
 asked the Embassy to rush an entrance visa for his wife and requested that his visa be considered
 separately. Marina believed that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was really
 planning to go only to Cuba. She testified that <quote speaker="">his basic desire was to get to
  Cuba by any means, and that all the rest of it was window dressing for that purpose.</quote>
 During the early days of the New Orleans period, <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person>&apos; marriage was more harmonious than it had been previously. Marina wrote: ...
 our family life in New Orleans was more peaceful. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person>
 took great satisfaction in showing me the city where he was born. We often went to the beach, the
 zoo, and the park. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> liked to go and hunt crabs. It is
 true, that he was not very pleased with his job ... We did not have very much money, and the birth
 of a new child involved new expenses ... As before, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person>
 spent a great deal of time reading. Marina testified, however, that after they had been in New
 Orleans for a while, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> became depressed and that
 she once found him alone in the dark crying. She wrote to Ruth Paine that his <quote speaker=""
  >love</quote> had ceased soon after Mrs. Paine had left New Orleans. Mrs. Paine testified,
 however, that she had noticed friction between <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the
  Oswalds</person> before she left. On <date daid="July-11">July 11</date>, Mrs. Paine wrote Marina
 that if <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not wish to live with her any more
 and preferred that she return to the Soviet Union, she could live at the Paines&apos; house.
 Although Mrs. Paine had long entertained this idea, this was the first time she explicitly made the
 invitation. She renewed the invitation on <date daid="July-12">July 12</date>, and again on <date
  daid="July-14">July 14</date>; she attempted to overcome any feeling which Marina might have that
 she would be a burden by stating that Marina could help with the housework and help her learn
 Russian, and that she would also provide a tax advantage. Marina replied that she had previously
 raised the subject of a separation and that it had led to arguments. She stated that she was happy
 and that for a considerable period of time <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had
 been good to her. She attributed this improved attitude to the fact that he was anticipating their
 second child. Marina turned down Mrs. Paine&apos;s invitation but said that she would take
 advantage of it if things became worse. Mrs. Paine replied that she was taking a trip north to
 visit her parents and would visit Marina in New Orleans about <date daid="September-18">September
  18</date>. She also suggested that Marina come to her house for the birth of the baby. On <date
  daid="July-6">July 6</date>, Eugene Murret, a cousin of <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> who was studying to be a Jesuit Priest in Mobile, Ala., wrote and asked if
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> could come to Mobile and speak at the Jesuit
 House of Studies about <quote speaker="">contemporary Russia and the practice of Communism
  there.</quote>
 <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> accepted, and on <date daid="July-27">July
  27</date> he and his family, joined by some of the Murrets, traveled to Mobile; Charles Murret
 paid the expenses. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> spoke concerning his
 observations in Russia and conducted a question and answer period; he impressed his listeners as
 articulate. He indicated that he had become disillusioned during his stay in Russia, and that in
 his opinion the best political system would be one which combined the best points of capitalism and
 communism. While he left his listeners with the impression that he was an atheist, he avoided a
 direct discussion of religion. The group returned to New Orleans on <date daid="July-28">July
  28</date>. In late May and early June, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had
 apparently begun to formulate plans for creating a New Orleans branch of the Fair Play for Cuba
 Committee. Using the name <quote speaker="">Lee Osborne</quote> he ordered a number of printed
 circulars demanding <quote speaker="">Hands off Cuba</quote> in large letters, and application
 forms and membership cards for the proposed chapter. On <date daid="August-5">August 5</date>, he
 visited a store managed by Carlos Bringuier, a Cuban refugee and avid opponent of Castro and the
 New Orleans delegate of the Cuban student directorate. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> indicated an interest in joining the struggle against Castro. He told Bringuier
 that he had been a marine and was trained in guerrilla warfare, and that he was willing not only to
 train Cubans to fight Castro but also to join the fight himself. The next day <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> returned to the store and left his <quote speaker=""
  >Guidebook for Marines</quote> for Bringuier. On <date daid="August-9">August 9</date>, Bringuier
 saw <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> passing out Fair Play for Cuba leaflets.
 Bringuier and his companions became angry and a dispute resulted. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> and the three Cuban exiles were arrested for disturbing the peace. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> spent the night in jail and was interviewed the next day
 by a lieutenant of the New Orleans Police Department. At <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person>&apos;s request, an FBI agent also interviewed him. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> maintained that he was a member of the New Orleans
 branch of the Fair Play for Cuba Committee which, he claimed, had 35 members. He stated also that
 he had been in touch with the president of that organization, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald-Alias">A. J. Hidell. Oswald</person> was in fact the only member of the
  <quote speaker="">New Orleans branch,</quote> which had never been chartered by the National Fair
 Play for Cuba Committee. Later that day <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was
 released on bail, and 2 days later he pleaded guilty to the charges against him and paid a $10
 fine. The charges against the Cuban exiles were dismissed. Marina testified that the arrest upset
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> and that he <quote speaker="">became less active,
  he cooled off a little</quote> after it. On <date daid="August-16">August 16</date>, Oswald,
 assisted by at least one other person who was a hired helper, again passed out Fair Play for Cuba
 literature, this time in front of the International Trade Mart. That night, television newscasts
 ran pictures of <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s activities. (This hindered
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s subsequent attempts to obtain employment
 in New Orleans.) Bringuier sent one of his friends to <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person>&apos;s home to pose as a Castro sympathizer and attempt to obtain information
 about Oswald, but <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> apparently saw through the
 ruse. William Stuckey, a radio broadcaster with a program called <quote speaker="">Latin Listening
  Post,</quote> had long been looking for a member of the Fair Play for Cuba Committee to appear on
 his program. He learned about <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> from Bringuier, and
 visited <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> on <date daid="August-17">August
  17</date>. Later that day, Stuckey recorded an interview with <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> which was cut to about 5 minutes and played back on the show that evening. Two
 days later, Stuckey asked the news director of the station if he could run the entire tape, but the
 director felt that a debate with a local opponent of Castro would be of greater public interest.
 Consequently, Stuckey arranged for a debate between <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> and Bringuier on a 25-minute daily public affairs program called <quote
  speaker="">Conversation Carte Blanche,</quote> which took place on <date daid="August-21">August
  21</date>. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> defended the Castro regime and
 discussed Marxism. He was put on the defensive when his defection to Russia was brought up, and
 Stuckey later testified that he thought that the program had finished the Fair Play for Cuba
 Committee in New Orleans. However, Stuckey also testified that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> seemed to be a clean-cut and intelligent person who conducted himself very well
 during the interviews and debates. Oswald wrote several times to <person perid="V.T.-Lee">V. T.
  Lee</person>, then national director of the Fair Play for Cuba Committee, telling him, sometimes
 in exaggerated terms, of his activities. He wrote also to the Communist Party and asked whether, in
 view of his prior defection, he should <quote speaker="">continue to fight, handicapped as it were,
  by ... [his] past record, [and] compete with anti-progressive forces, above-ground or ... should
  always remain in the background, i.e., underground.</quote> The Party replied that <quote
  speaker="">often it is advisable for some people to remain in the background, not
  underground.</quote> And although <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> wrote four
 letters to <person perid="V.T.-Lee">V. T. Lee</person> during the summer, there is no evidence that
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> heard from him after <date daid="May-29">May
  29</date>. Ruth Paine arrived in New Orleans on <date daid="September-20">September 20</date>, and
 spent three nights with <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>. During
 this stay, Mrs. Paine found relations between them much improved. Nonetheless, it was decided that
 Marina would go back with her to Irving for the birth of the baby. Marina and Mrs. Paine toured
 Bourbon Street while <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> stayed home and did some
 packing for Marina&apos;s return to Texas. On Sunday, <date daid="September-22">September
 22</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> and Mrs. Paine finished loading the
 station wagon with <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>&apos;
 household belongings. Return to Top <place plaid="Mexico-City">MEXICO CITY</place>
 <person perid="Marina-Oswald">Marina Oswald</person> testified that sometime in August her husband
 first told her of his plan to go to Mexico and from there to Cuba, where he planned to stay; he had
 given up a plan to hijack an airplane and fly directly to Cuba, which plan Marina consistently
 opposed. On <date daid="September-17">September 17</date>, he obtained from the Mexican consulate
 general in New Orleans a <quote speaker="">Tourist Card,</quote> FM-8 No. 24085, good for one
 journey into Mexico for no longer than 15 days. Typed in the blank, <quote speaker="">Appelidos y
  nombre</quote> was <quote speaker="">Lee, Harvey Oswald,</quote>
 <quote speaker="">Fotogrofo</quote>; the intended destination was shown as Mexico City. (The comma
 between <quote speaker="">Lee</quote> and <quote speaker="">Harvey</quote> seems to have been an
 error.)1101 On the application <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> stated that he was
 employed at <quote speaker="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">640 Rampart</quote>; he was in fact unemployed. (See
 Commission Exhibits Nos. 2478, 2481, p. 300.) Marina and <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald"
  >June</person> departed with Mrs. Ruth Paine for Irving on the morning of <date
  daid="September-23">September 23</date>. Before she left, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> told Marina that she should not tell anyone about his impending trip to Mexico.
 Marina kept this secret until after the assassination. On the previous day, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s landlord had seen Mrs. Paine&apos;s car being
 packed and had asked <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> whose rent was about 15 days
 overdue, whether he was leaving. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told him that
 Marina was leaving temporarily but that he would remain. A neighbor testified that on the evening
 of <date daid="September-24">September 24</date>, he saw Oswald, carrying two pieces of luggage,
 hurriedly leave the Magazine Street apartment and board a bus. Though uncertain of the exact date,
 a city busdriver recalls that at the same time of day and at the same location he picked up a man
 who was carrying two suitcases of different sizes and helped him place them so that they would not
 disturb the other passengers. The driver remembers that the man asked directions to the Greyhound
 bus station. He discharged the passenger at an intersection where he could board a Canal Street car
 and transfer to another bus which would go past the Greyhound and Continental Trailways stations.
 The landlord found <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s apartment vacant on
  <date daid="September-25">September 25</date>. Oswald appears to have taken with him a
 Spanish-English dictionary; his address book; his <date daid="1963">1963 passport</date> and old
 passport; his correspondence with the Communist Party and with the Soviet Embassy in Washington,
 some of which was in Russian; proof of his marriage; newspaper clippings concerning his arrest and
 his interest in the activities of the Fair Play for Cuba Committee (activities which, Marina
 testified, he had undertaken because he thought that they would help him when he got to Cuba);
 evidence that he was the <quote speaker="">Director</quote> of the New Orleans chapter of the
 Committee; and various other cards, such as a work card, which he had obtained in Russia. He took
 also several sheets of notepaper on which he had written a summary of important events in his life
 which he presumably intended to call to the attention of Cuban and Soviet officials in Mexico City
 to convince them to let him enter Cuba. On these sheets he had recorded facts about his Marine
 service, including the dates of his enlistment and discharge, the places where he had served, and
 the diplomas that he had received from military school. Recorded also were notes on his stay in the
 Soviet Union, his early interest in Communist literature, his ability to speak Russian, his
 organization of the New Orleans chapter of the Fair Play for Cuba Committee, his contact with
 police authorities in connection with his work for the Committee, and his experience in <quote
  speaker="">street agitation,</quote> as a <quote speaker="">radio speaker and lecturer,</quote>
 and as a photographer. The two pieces of luggage which <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> took with him were a small, blue, zipper bag and a large, olive-colored bag, both
 made of cloth. He carried the smaller bag with him throughout the trip, but, at least from Nuevo
 Laredo to Mexico City, checked the larger one through to his destination. Oswald remained in New
 Orleans until <date daid="September-25">September 25</date>. His precise whereabouts on the night
 of <date daid="September-24">September 24</date> are uncertain, but in view of his limited
 finances, he probably returned to the apartment to sleep after checking his luggage at a bus
 station or spent the night at an inexpensive hotel or roominghouse. Some time after 5 a. m. on
  <date daid="September-25">September 25</date>, he collected a Texas unemployment compensation
 check for $33 at his New Orleans post office box. He cashed the check between 8 a.m. and noon at a
 store about six blocks from his apartment on Magazine Street. This gave him about $200 for the trip
 to Mexico. He left New Orleans by bus, probably on Continental Trailways Bus No. 5121, departing
 New Orleans at 12:20 p.m. on <date daid="September-25">September 25</date>, and scheduled to arrive
 in Houston at 10:50 p.m.; that bus is the only one on which <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> could have left New Orleans after noon on <date daid="September-25">September
  25</date> and arrived in Houston before midnight. Sometime in the evening he called the home of
 Horace Elroy Twiford, a member of the Socialist Labor Party who had received <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s name from the party&apos;s headquarters in New
 York and sent him a copy of its official publication, the <quote speaker="">Weekly People.</quote>
 Mrs. Twiford, who answered the telephone, believes that the call was made locally, before 10 p.m.
 It may have been made from Beaumont or some other stop on the route; however, in view of the bus
 schedule, it probably was made in Houston later than Mrs. Twiford remembered. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told Mrs. Twiford that he was a member of the Fair Play
 for Cuba Committee and that he hoped to see her husband for a few hours that evening before he flew
 to Mexico. He wanted also to find out how Twiford had obtained his name and address. Mrs. Twiford
 told <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> that her husband, a merchant seaman, was at
 sea but would be happy to see him at some other time; she offered to take a message. Oswald said
 that he could not await her husband&apos;s return because he was flying to Mexico. The Twifords
 have stated that they had no other contact with <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>.
 An employee of the U.S. Selective Service System has stated that an individual calling himself
  <quote speaker="">Harvey Oswald</quote> appeared at her office in Austin, Tex., immediately after
 lunch on <date daid="September-25">September 25</date>, and discussed with her the possibility of
 rectifying his undesirable discharge from the Marine Corps. Despite the employee&apos;s
 reputability and apparent sincerity, all of the information which she furnished with respect to
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s appearance and conversation could have
 been derived from news media, consciously or unconsciously, by the time she told the FBI her story.
 Other persons in Austin who, according to the employee&apos;s testimony, should also have observed
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> failed to corroborate her testimony. No other
 evidence tending to show that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was in Austin at
 this time has been discovered. The telephone call which <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> made to the Twifords on the evening of <date daid="September-25">September
  25</date>, indicates that he was either in Houston or on his way there when he made it, since the
 purpose of the call was to make an appointment to see Twiford in Houston that evening. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> could not have left New Orleans on <date
  daid="September-25">September 25</date>, been in Austin 521 miles away by early afternoon, and
 returned 162 miles to Houston by night unless he traveled by air; airline records contain no
 indication that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was on such flights. It is very
 unlikely that he had with him enough money beyond what he needed for the trip to Mexico City to
 take such flights, and the poor state of his finances at this time plus his well-established
 frugality make it extremely unlikely that he would have considered it worthwhile to do so even if
 he could. There is no evidence that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was in such a
 hurry to reach Mexico that he would have felt it necessary to travel by airplane rather than a less
 expensive means of travel. He took a bus from Houston to Mexico City, lived very inexpensively
 there, and took a bus back to Dallas; there is no apparent reason why he would have interrupted
 such an inexpensive trip to fly to Austin and then to Houston. He told a passenger whom he met on
 the next leg of his trip that he had come from New Orleans, and made no reference to Austin. On
  <date daid="September-26">September 26</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 boarded Continental Trailways bus No. 5133 in Houston and departed at 2:35 a.m. for Laredo, Tex.,
 via Corpus Christi and Alice. Two British tourists, Dr. and Mrs. John B. McFarland, who boarded No.
 5133 in Houston, noticed <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> when they awoke at about
 6 a.m. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told them that he was going to Cuba via
 Mexico City, and they inferred from conversation with him that he had left New Orleans early in the
 afternoon of <date daid="September-25">September 25</date> and that he was going to Cuba via Mexico
 City. He said also that he was secretary of the New Orleans branch of the Fair Play for Cuba
 Committee and that he hoped to see Fidel Castro in Cuba. The bus was scheduled to arrive in Laredo
 at approximately 1:20 p.m. Oswald crossed the border from Laredo to Nuevo Laredo, Mexico, between
 1:30 and 2 p.m. From Nuevo Laredo, he traveled to Mexico City aboard bus No. 516 of the Flecha Roja
 Bus Line, which departed at 2:15 p.m. and was scheduled to arrive in Mexico City at 9:45 a.m. on
 the following day; he held baggage claim check No. 320435. He was seen on the bus by the McFarlands
 and by two Australian girls who boarded the bus on the evening of <date daid="September-26"
  >September 26</date> at Monterrey. He occupied the seat next to an elderly Englishman, who told
 the girls that the young man sitting next to him apparently had been to Mexico before. The man next
 to <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was probably Albert Osborne, a native of the
 British Isles who has worked as an itinerant preacher in the Southern United States and Mexico for
 many years. Osborne denied that he sat beside Oswald; but in view of his inconsistent and untrue
 responses to Federal investigators concerning matters not directly related to Oswald, the
 Commission believes that his denial cannot be credited. It appeared to the other passengers on the
 bus that Osborne and <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had not previously met;
 extensive investigation has revealed no other contact between them. In the course of the 20-hour
 bus trip, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> initiated two conversations with the
 Australian girls, during which he mentioned his visit to Russia and recommended the Hotel Cuba in
 Mexico City as a clean and cheap" hotel; he told them, apparently falsely, that he had stayed there
 on previous occasions. He said that when he had seen them board the bus with their heavy suitcases,
 he had been under the impression that they were Mexican and had therefore asked the man next to him
 how to say <quote speaker="">How can I help you?</quote> in Spanish. From this they inferred that
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not speak Spanish, an impression which is
 shared by every witness who met <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> on his trip and
 is supported by notations which he made on documents that he carried. He got off the bus at every
 stop and ate large meals, always eating by himself; the girls thought he ate so much because he
 could not make himself understood in Spanish and had to order by pointing at the menu. The bus
 arrived in Mexico City 15 minutes late, at 10 a.m. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> left the bus station by himself and had no known further contact with any of the
 people with whom he had spoken on the bus. Oswald registered at the Hotel del Comercio within an
 hour of his arrival in Mexico City. He stayed there throughout his visit. The hotel, located not
 far from the commercial heart of the city and within four blocks of the bus station, is one of a
 group of hotels located near the intercity bus terminals and has perhaps the best appearance of the
 group. It is known by personnel in other hotels that the owner of the Hotel del Comercio can
 understand and speak a little English. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> registered
 as <quote speaker="">Lee, Harvey Oswald,</quote> and gave his occupation as <quote speaker=""
  >photo.</quote> He had room 18 which cost $1.28 per day. After he had registered, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> turned promptly to the task of obtaining permission to
 enter Cuba. Mexican officials would not permit a U.S. citizen without a Cuban visa to board a plane
 for Cuba even if he had an American passport, but would permit passage if he had a visa even though
 the passport proscribed travel to Cuba. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> had a
  <date daid="1963">1963</date> American passport (stamped invalid for travel to Cuba)1154 but had
 neither a regular Cuban visa nor an intransit visa which would permit a short stay in Cuba on his
 way to Russia or some other country. His address book contained the telephone number and address of
 a Cuban airline, but there is evidence that he never visited its office. He visited the Cuban
 Embassy on Friday, <date daid="September-27">September 27</date> and spoke with Senora Silvia
 Tirado de Duran, a Mexican citizen employed there. Senora Duran later made a signed statement to
 the Mexican police that Oswald: ... applied for a visa to Cuba in transit to Russia and based his
 application on his presentation of his passport in which it was recorded that, he had been living
 in the latter country for a period of three years, his work permit from that same country written
 in the Russian language and letters in the same language, as well as proof of his being married to
 a woman of Russian nationality and being the apparent Director in the city of New Orleans of the
 organization called <quote speaker="">Fair Play for Cuba</quote> with the desire that he should be
 accepted as a <quote speaker="">friend</quote> of the Cuban Revolution ... He apparently also
 stated that he was a member of the Communist Party and displayed documents which he claimed to be
 evidence of his membership. He said that he intended to go to Cuba on <date daid="September-30"
  >September 30</date> and to remain there for 2 weeks, or longer if possible, and then go on to
 Russia. Senora Duran took down the relevant date and filled out the appropriate application.
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> left the Embassy but was to return in the
 afternoon. Then, or possibly even before his initial visit to the Cuban Embassy <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> went to the Soviet Embassy where he spoke with either
 Pavel Antonovich Yatskov or Valeriy Vladimirovich Kostikov. They are both consular officials
 serving also as agents of the KGB. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> later said
 that he had dealt with <quote speaker="">Kostin,</quote> undoubtedly a reference to Kostikov. He
 was unable to obtain a Soviet visa then. Marina said that the officials at the Soviet Embassy
  <quote speaker="">refused to have anything to do with him.</quote> Oswald returned to the Cuban
 Embassy later that afternoon, this time bringing with him passport photographs which he may have
 obtained in the United States. Senora Duran telephoned the Soviet Embassy to inquire about the
 status of <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s Russian visa and was told that
 there would be a delay of about 4 months. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> became
  <quote speaker="">highly agitated and angry,</quote> particularly when he learned that he could
 not obtain an intransit visa to Cuba before he acquired a Russian visa. Senora Duran called the
 Cuban consul, then Eusibio Azque, to speak to him. The discussion between <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> and Azque developed into a heated argument, which ended
 when Azque told <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> that in his opinion people like
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> were harming the Cuban Revolution and that so
 far as Azque was concerned, he would not give <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> a
 visa. Senora Duran wrote her name and the phone number of the Embassy on a piece of paper which she
 gave to <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> in case he wished to contact her again.
 He copied this information into his address book. Senora Duran forwarded the Cuban visa application
 to Havana ;1168 the Cuban Ministry of Foreign Affairs replied on <date daid="October-15">October
  15</date> that the visa could be issued only after <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> had obtained a Russian visa. (See Commission Exhibit, No. 2564, p. 303.) Oswald
 contacted the Russian and Cuba Embassies again during his stay in Mexico. He had no greater success
 than he had before. Marina testified that when he returned to Texas, he was convinced that his trip
 had been a failure and disappointed at having been unable to go to Cuba. A month later, in a
 painstakingly composed letter to the Soviet Embassy in Washington, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> ascribed his failure to <quote speaker="">a gross breach
  of regulations</quote> on the part of the Cuban Embassy. <quote speaker="">Of corse,</quote> he
 wrote, <quote speaker="">the Soviet Embassy was not at fault, they were, as I say
  unprepared.</quote> The hotel maid said that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 generally was gone by the time she arrived at 9 a.m. The night watchman said he usually returned at
 about midnight, which is not unusual, in view of the late hour at which Mexico City&apos;s evening
 activities begin. He ate several lunches at a small restaurant immediately adjacent to the hotel,
 coming to the restaurant shortly after 2 p.m., and ordering food by pointing to the menu,
 apparently with some consideration of cost; he spent between 40 and 48 cents for each meal. He ate
 the soup of the day, rice, and either meat or eggs, but refused dessert and coffee; the waitress
 concluded that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not realize that the items
 which he refused were included in the price of the lunch. He was seen with no other person either
 at his hotel or at the restaurant. A hotel guest stated that on one occasion he sat down at a table
 with <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> because there was no empty table in the
 restaurant, but that neither spoke to the other because of the language barrier. Although the
 Soviet and Cuban Embassies are within two blocks of each other, they are some distance from <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s hotel. He must, therefore, have traversed a
 substantial portion of the city on more than one occasion. Marina testified that he told her that
 he had seen a bullfight, which would normally have been on Sunday afternoon, and that he had
 visited museums and done some sightseeing. He apparently also saw one or more motion pictures,
 either American with Spanish subtitles or Mexican with English subtitles. From notations in his
 Spanish-English dictionary and on his guide map of Mexico City, it appears that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> intended to attend a jai alai game but he almost
 certainly did not do so. He purchased several postcards depicting bullfights and tourist
 attractions, which he brought back to Marina. She had told him be- fore he left that she would like
 Mexican silver bracelets as a souvenir, and he brought her a silver bracelet inscribed with her
 name. Marina suspected, almost certainly correctly, that the bracelet, of Japanese origin, did not
 come from Mexico. No such jewelry is known to be sold in or around Mexico City, because of a high
 duty but the bracelet is of a type commonly sold in 5-and-10-cent stores in Dallas. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not buy the Mexican phonograph records which Marina
 had requested, despite the notation, <quote speaker="">records,</quote> which he had placed in his
 dictionary. On Monday, <date daid="September-30">September 30</date>, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> began to prepare for his return to the United States. He
 appeared at the Agencia de Viages, Transportes Chihuahuenses, and purchased international exchange
 orders costing $20.30 for travel on a Transportes del Norte bus from Mexico City to Laredo and by
 Greyhound bus directly from Laredo to Dallas. The travel agency made a reservation for him on
 Transportes del Notre bus No. 332, departing Mexico City at 8:30 a.m. on <date daid="October-2"
  >October 2</date>. The seat, No. 12, was reserved in the name of the travel agency, which recorded
 the reservation in the name of <quote speaker="">H. O. Lee.</quote> The employee who made the
 reservation testified that he probably wrote the name that way because he was copying from <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>&apos;s tourist card, which read <quote speaker=""
   ><person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee, Harvey Oswald</person>.</quote> (The manifest for
 Transportes Frontera bus No. 340, leaving Mexico City for Monterrey and Nuevo Laredo at 1 p.m. on
 Wednesday, <date daid="October-2">October 2</date>, 1963, contains the name <quote speaker=""
  >Oswld</quote> [sic], which apparently was added to the manifest after the trip; in any event,
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not take bus 340.) On <date daid="October-1"
  >October 1</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> paid his hotel bill through
 that night. The hotel night watchman remembers helping <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> obtain a taxicab at about 6:30 or 7 on the following morning. Transportes del
 Norte bus No. 332 left as scheduled at about 8:30 a.m.; at Monterrey the passengers were shifted to
 a relief bus, No. 373, scheduled to depart for Laredo at 10 p.m. that evening. Fellow passengers
 recall that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was pulled off the bus by Mexican
 officials at the border, because of some alleged irregularity in his Mexican tourist papers; one
 passenger overheard him mumbling complaints about the Mexican immigration officials when he
 returned to the bus. They remember also that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was
 hurriedly <quote speaker="">gulping</quote> down a banana after the bus reached customs, perhaps
 because he believed that he could not take fruit into the United States. (Marina has testified that
 her husband liked bananas and frequently ate them.)1201 One of the passengers testified that
  <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> annoyed him by keeping his overhead light on to
 read after 10 p.m. He may have conversed with an elderly woman on the bus, but he was not traveling
 with her. At about 1:35 a.m. on <date daid="October-3">October 3</date>, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> crossed the International Bridge from Nuevo Laredo into
 Texas. He traveled from Laredo to Dallas via San Antonio, on Greyhound bus No. 1265, substantially
 following Interstate Route 35 for the entire trip leaving Laredo at 3 a.m. and arriving in Dallas
 at about 2:20 p.m. on the same day. <place plaid="Dallas">DALLAS</place> Oswald did not contact his
 wife immediately when he returned to Dallas. He went to the office of the employment commission,
 where he filed an unemployment compensation claim and announced that he was again looking for work.
 He spent the night at the YMCA, where he registered as a serviceman in order to avoid paying the
 membership fee. On the following day, he applied for a job as a typesetter trainee at the Padgett
 Printing Co. He made a favorable impression on the department foreman, but the plant superintendent
 called Jaggars-Chiles-Stovall and decided not to hire <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> because of the unfavorable responses which his inquiries produced. Later that
 day, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> telephoned Marina and asked her to have Mrs.
 Paine pick him up in Dallas. Marina refused, and he hitchhiked out to the Paine home, where he
 spent part or all of the weekend. Marina testified that although her husband <quote speaker=""
  >changed for the better</quote> and treated her better after his Mexican trip, she did not want to
 live with him because she was pregnant and thought it would be better <quote speaker="">to be with
  a woman who spoke English and Russian.</quote> On Monday, <date daid="October-7">October 7</date>,
 Mrs. Paine drove <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> to the bus station, and he
 returned to Dallas to look for a job and a place to live. Oswald thought that the YMCA was too
 expensive for him, and intended to rent a room. He inquired about a room at <place
  plaid="1026-North-Beckley">1026 North Beckley</place>, where he lived later, but on <date
  daid="October-7">October 7</date> there were no vacancies. He next responded to a <quote
  speaker="">For Rent</quote> sign at a rooming house at <place plaid="621-Marsalis-Street">621
  Marsalis Street</place>. He obtained a room, for which he paid the weekly rent of $7 in advance,
 and moved in on the same day. He immediately resumed his job-hunting, relying partially on
 referrals by the employment commission. He spent much of the time when he was not looking for work
 in his room. He telephoned his wife daily. She wrote: <quote speaker="">Lee called twice a day, was
  worried about my health and about <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person>.</quote> On
 Friday, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> told his landlady, Mrs. Mary Bledsoe,
 that he was going to Irving for the weekend but would return the following week. She refused to
 rent the room to him for another week because she didn&apos;t like him. Oswald spent the weekend of
  <date daid="October-12-13">October 12-13</date> at Mrs. Paine&apos;s home, during which time she
 gave him a driving lesson. He told her that he had received the last of the unemployment checks due
 him, and that it had been smaller than the previous ones. Mrs. Paine testified that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was extremely discouraged because his wife was expecting
 a baby, he had no job prospects in sight, and he no longer had any source of income. On Monday,
 Mrs. Paine drove <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> into Dallas, since she had other
 business there. He picked up his bag from Mrs. Bledsoe&apos;s roominghouse and later that day
 rented a room at <place plaid="1026-North-Beckley-Avenue">1026 North Beckley Avenue</place> from
 Mrs. A. C. Johnson for $8 a week. He registered as <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald-Alias">O. H.
  Lee</person> and moved in immediately. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> felt that
 this room was more comfortable than the previous one, particularly because he had television and
 refrigerator privileges. He apparently continued to spend most of his evenings in his room. He
 borrowed books from the library and had subscriptions to various periodicals, including Time, the
 Worker, the Militant, and some Russian periodicals. On that Monday, Mrs. Paine mentioned <person
  perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald">the Oswalds</person>&apos; financial and employment problems
 to neighbors whom she was visiting. Mrs. Linnie Mac Randle, who was also present, remarked that she
 thought that her younger brother, Buell Wesley Frazier, who worked at the Texas School Book
 Depository, had said that there was a job opening there. When Marina heard of this, she asked Mrs.
 Paine to call the Depository to see if there was an opening. Mrs. Paine called Roy S. Truly,
 superintendent of the Depository, who indicated that he would talk to <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> if he would apply in person. When <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> telephoned the Paine house on Monday evening, Mrs. Paine
 told him about this possibility. On the next day, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 was interviewed by Truly and hired in a temporary capacity. He began work on Wednesday, <date
  daid="October-16">October 16</date>. His duties were to fill book orders; his hours were 8 a.m. to
 4:45 p.m., for which he received $1.25 an hour. Both <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >the Oswalds</person> were elated with the new job, although it apparently required little skill
 or experience and he indicated that he still hoped to obtain a better job. He did a satisfactory
 job at the Depository, but he kept to himself and very few of his fellow employees got to know him.
 During his first week at work, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> became acquainted
 with Frazier, with whom he arranged to ride to Irving on weekends. On Friday, <date
  daid="October-18">October 18</date>, Frazier drove him from work to the Paine home; since it was
 his birthday, Marina and Ruth Paine had arranged a small celebration. On Sunday, he stayed with
  <person perid="June-Lee-Oswald">June</person> and the Paine children, while Mrs. Paine drove
 Marina to Parkland Hospital where she gave birth to a second daughter, Rachel. He went to work on
 Monday, but that evening visited Marina in the hospital and spent the night in Irving. Marina
 wrote: Monday evening <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee</person> visited me in the hospital. He
 was very happy at the birth of another daughter and even wept a little. He said that two daughters
 were better for each other--two sisters. He stayed with me about two hours. Oswald returned to
 Dallas the next morning. Oswald wrote to Arnold Johnson of the <person
  perid="Communist-Party-U.S.A.">Communist Party, U.S.A.</person>, that on the evening of <date
  daid="October-23">October 23</date>, he had attended an <quote speaker="">ultra right</quote>
 meeting headed by Gen. Edwin A. Walker. Two evenings later, he accompanied Michael Paine to a
 meeting of the American Civil Liberties Union, held at Southern Methodist University. At this
 meeting, a statement was made to the effect that members of the John Birch Society should not be
 considered anti-Semitic; <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> rose and stated that at
 the meeting which he had attended 2 days earlier, he had heard a number of anti-Semitic and
 anti-Catholic statements. Later in the evening, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 became involved in a discussion with several people, including Frank Krystinik, who was employed
 with Paine at the Bell Helicopter plant. During this conversation, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> expressed Marxist views and declared that he was a
 Marxist, although denying that he was a Communist. He admitted that the United States was superior
 to the Soviet Union in the area of civil liberties and praised President Kennedy for his work in
 that connection. Krystinik testified that he got the impression that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not fully understand the views he was expounding.
 Throughout that week <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> telephoned his wife to
 inquire about her health and that of the baby. He spent the weekend at the Paine home, to which
 Marina and Rachel had returned during the week. On Friday, <date daid="November-1">November
  1</date>, he obtained post office box No. 6225 at the <place
  plaid="Terminal-Annex-Post-Office-Station">Terminal Annex Post Office Station</place>. He
 indicated that the box would also be used to receive mail for the Fair Play for Cuba Committee and
 the American Civil Liberties Union. Once again he spent the weekend in Irving. Throughout this
 period, the FBI had been aware of the whereabouts of <person perid="Marina-and-Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >the Oswalds</person>. There was a record in the Dallas office of the FBI that <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> subscribed to the Worker, engaged in Fair Play for Cuba
 Committee activities and had traveled to Mexico. An FBI agent visited the Paine home on November
 and, accompanied by another agent, again on <date daid="November-5">November 5</date>, and spoke
 briefly with Mrs. Paine. On neither occasion was <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>
 present. Ruth Paine noted the agent&apos;s name and telephone number and, in accordance with her
 husband&apos;s instructions, Marina noted the license number of the agent&apos;s automobile, all of
 which was subsequently reported to <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person>. Both Mrs.
 Paine and Marina testified that <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> was troubled by
 the FBI&apos;s interest in him. He declared that the FBI was <quote speaker="">trying to
  inhibit</quote> his activities, and wrote the Soviet Embassy in Washington: The Federal Bureu of
 Investigation is not now interested in my activities in the progressive organization <quote
  speaker="">Fair Play for Cuba Committee</quote> of which I was secretary in New Orleans (state
 Louisiana) since I no longer reside in that state. However, the F.B.I. has visted us here in
 Dallas, Texas, on <date daid="November-1">November 1</date>st. Agent James P. Hasty warned me that
 if I engaged in F.P.C.C. activities in Texas the F.B.I. will again take an <quote speaker=""
  >interest</quote> in me. This agent also &apos;suggested&apos; to Marina Nichilayeva that she
 could remain in the United States under F.B.I. &apos;protection&apos;, that is, she could defect
 from the Soviet Union, of couse, I and my wife strongly protested these tactics by the notorious
 F.B.I. Please inform us of the arrival of our Soviet entrance visa&apos;s as soon as they come.
 (See Commission Exhibit 15, p. 311.) Marina testified that the statements, both by and to the FBI
 agents, to which her husband referred in this letter, were in fact never made. The following
 Friday, <date daid="November-8">November 8</date>, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> as usual drove to the Paine house with Frazier. On Saturday Mrs. Paine took him
 to the Texas Drivers&apos; License Examining Station, but because it was an election day the
 station was closed. <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> stayed at the Paines through
 Monday, <date daid="November-11">November 11</date>, which was Veterans Day. During the weekend,
 Mrs. Paine gave <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> a second driving lesson. Oswald
 did not go to Irving on the next weekend. His wife had asked him not to come because Michael Paine,
 with whom <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> did not get along, would be there to
 celebrate his daughter&apos;s birthday. Also, she felt that because he had stayed for 3 days the
 preceding weekend, he would abuse Mrs. Paine&apos;s hospitality if he returned so soon. <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> telephoned Marina on Saturday afternoon and said that he
 had returned to the drivers&apos; license examining station that morning but had not waited because
 there was a long line. On Sunday, <date daid="November-17">November 17</date>, at Marina&apos;s
 request, Ruth Paine telephoned <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> at the Beckley
 Avenue number, which he had given to Marina. When she asked for him, she was told that no one by
 that name lived at the address, which greatly surprised her. On the next day, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> telephoned his wife. When she indicated that she had
 been upset by the fact that there had been no <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Lee Oswald</person>
 at the number which she had asked Mrs. Paine to call <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald"
  >Oswald</person> became angry; he said that he was using a fictitious name and that she should not
 have called the Beckley Avenue number. He did not telephone on the following day, which was
 unusual. On the morning of Thursday, <date daid="November-21">November 21</date>, <person
  perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> asked Frazier to take him to Irving when he went home
 that evening, saying that he wanted to pick up some curtain rods. His arrival was a surprise
 because he generally asked Mrs. Paine&apos;s permission before arriving for a visit. The women
 thought that he had come to Irving because he felt badly about arguing with his wife about the use
 of the fictitious name. He said that he was lonely, because he had not come the preceding weekend,
 and told Marina that he <quote speaker="">wanted to make his peace</quote> with her. He spent the
 time before dinner on the lawn playing with his daughter. However, when he attempted to talk to his
 wife she would not answer, which upset him. He asked her to live with him in Dallas, and she
 refused. After supper, <person perid="Lee-Harvey-Oswald">Oswald</person> watched television while
 the women cleaned the house and prepared their children for bed. He retired early in the evening at
 about 9. </wrstart>
